Guide to the de Groot Family Photograph Collection 1853-[1967], undated PR 120
New-York Historical Society
de Groot Family Photograph Collection
1853-[1967], undated
New-York Historical Society
PR 120
1.88 Linear feet (3 boxes)
Collection of photographs of Adelaide Milton de Groot (1876-1967) and portraits of members of her extended family including her parents, siblings, cousins, and their ancestors. Includes photographs of war work in France during World War I.
Provenance
Gift of Adelaide Milton de Groot in December 1941 and March 1942.
Access Restrictions
Open to qualified researchers, by appointment only.
Photocopying undertaken by staff only. Limited to 20 photocopies per day per person. Suitability of the original for photocopying is at the discretion of the staff. Neither blueprints nor tracings can be copied under any circumstances. Duplication of large-format items will be done by the house photographer. See Print Room guidelines for details.
Biographical Note
Adelaide Milton de Groot (1876-1967) was the daughter of China trade ship owner William de Groot (1825-1898) and his second wife Elizabeth King Hawley (1833-1926). A painter, art collector and philanthropist, Miss de Groot was born in New York City and moved with her family to Nice, France, in 1891. She lived in Europe for forty years before returning to New York in 1933.
Scope and Content Note
The de Groot Family Photograph Collection contains portraits of Adelaide Milton de Groot (1876-1967) and members of her extended family including her parents, siblings, cousins, and their ancestors. Interested in genealogy, she documented the families related to her by marriage, namely the Bosworth, Brantingham, Foote, Hastings, Hawley and Robinson families. Her New York cousins included yachtsman, composer and photographer Frank Seymour Hastings (1853-1924) and his brother, the noted architect Thomas Hastings (1860-1929), the sons of the Reverend Thomas Samuel Hastings (1827-1911) and Fanny de Groot. Adelaide de Groot's sister Elizabeth (1874-1898) married an Italian diplomat, Guilio Caravadossi, the Count of Aspremonte; the collection includes many photographs of the Caravadossis and "La Tour Aspremont Baumettes," their family home in Nice. There are also photographs, including a post-mortem portrait, of their daughter Teresina (1899-1917). Other photographs in the collection include portraits of family friends such as the author Baron Gabriel d'Orgeval, and group portraits that include various touring American friends and members of the expatriate community prior to the second World War. In addition, there are photographs of Miss de Groot's activities with the American Colony Hospital at Nice (1915-1918) and the Daughters of the American Revolution (Philadelphia and Washington chapters visiting Paris in 1932). Most of the photographs are annotated with information about the sitters including, in some cases, details of the colors and fabrics of their clothing; some annotations are extensive and narrative, describing the personalities, relationships and life situations of the subjects.
Arrangement
Files are arranged alphabetically by sitter, with miscellaneous and unidentified photographs at the end.
Related Material at the The New-York Historical Society
Additional de Groot family photographs in The New-York Historical Society Library are located in the de Groot Family Papers held in the Manuscript Department; additional family papers are in BV de Groot. Two annotated family photograph albums holding many of the same and similar images as PR 120 are available in the Department of Prints, Photographs and Architectural Collections in the Album File (PR 002); images of several de Groot, Brantingham and Hawley family members are in the Cased Photographs File (PR 012).
Military nursing -- France.; Hospitals -- France -- Nice.; Photographic prints.; Tintypes (prints); Portraits.; Women art collectors; Postmortem photography; Upper class -- New York (State) -- New York.; World War, 1914-1918 -- War work -- France.; Women in charitable work; American Colony Hospital (Nice, France); Bosworth family; Brantingham (Family); Caravadossi (Family); Caravadossi, Elizabeth Hawley de Groot, 1874-1898; Caravadossi, Giulio; Daughters of the American Revolution; De Groot family; Foote family; Hastings family; Hastings, Frank Seymour; Hastings, Thomas, 1860-1929; Hawley (Family); Le Barrois d'Orgeval, Gabriel, baron, 1879-1932; Robinson family; Tour Aspremont (Nice, France)
- unspecified
  Scope and Contents note
  Files are arranged alphabetically by sitter, with miscellaneous and unidentified photographs at the end. Oversize photographs are filed in Box 3.
  - Bosworth family, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Brantingham family, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Caravadossi, Elizabeth Hawley de Groot, [1873]-1900 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Caravadossi, Guilo, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Caravadossi, Teresina, 1900-1917 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Caravadossi family home, La Tour d'Aspremont Baumettes, Nice, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - de Forest family, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - de Groot, Adelaide Milton--Childhood photographs, [1876]-[1967] (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - de Groot, Adelaide Milton--Coming out photographs, 1893 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - de Groot, Adelaide Milton--Portraits by Frank Seymour Hastings, [1909] (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - de Groot, Adelaide Milton--Hospital work and World War I, 1915-1918 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - de Groot, Adelaide Milton--Portraits by Count Broel Plater, 1919-1920 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - de Groot, Adelaide Milton--Portraits in costume, [1922] (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - de Groot, Adelaide Milton--Daughters of the American Revolution activities, 1932 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - de Groot, Adelaide Milton--Miscellaneous, 1931-1932, undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - de Groot, Adelaide and Elizabeth, undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - de Groot, Elizabeth King Hawley, 1870-[1929] (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - de Groot, Grace LaTourette, [1855], undated (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - de Groot, Hugo and Maria (engravings), undated (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - de Groot, Isabella Graham Brittain, undated (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - de Groot, Mary Nesbitt, [1865] (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - de Groot, William, 1853-1898 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - de Groot family groups, 1891-1892 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Foote family, undated (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Hastings family, undated (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Hawley family, undated (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - McClellen, George, undated (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Robinson family, undated (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Friends, 1926-1938, undated (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Places, undated (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Unidentified men, undated (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Unidentified women and children, undated (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Caravadossi, Elizabeth Hawley de Groot, undated (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - Caravadossi, Teresina, 1917 (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - de Groot, Adelaide Milton--Portrait, [1870] (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - de Groot, Adelaide Milton--Portrait with her sister Elizabeth, [1870] (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - de Groot, Adelaide Milton--Portrait, 1917 (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - de Groot, Adelaide Milton--Portraits, [1960-1967] (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - de Groot, Elizabeth King Hawley, [1885] (Box 3, Folder 39)
  - Hastings, Frank Seymour, home music room, [1910] (Box 3, Folder 40)